Can you all hear me?
>> We hear you sir.
>> Okay. And is this is the audio clear?
>> Yep.
>> Right. Okay. So,
uh we have just completed our series of
lectures on training neural networks. We
are moving on to our second topic
convolutional neural networks. In the
last class we saw what a convolutional
neural network was. We derived it from
basic princip principles. How scanning
for a pattern uh is gives us position
invariance in pattern detection. about
how just reordering the scan gives us
a kind of network that we are all
familiar with as the convolutional
neural network. But the genesis of CNN's
was not from the principle of scanning
for patterns. It actually started from a
biological perspective and it actually
all started from cats. So for the
longest time
we didn't really know how the human
visual system worked. How do animals
see? What is the neural process from the
eye to recognition?
There was a lot of early research on
this but much of it was based on
behavioral and behavioral analysis. We
would researchers would study behavioral
judgment in response to visual
stimulation like these. Now, this
picture on the left, what do you guys
see in this picture to the left?
What do you folks see? Anyone?
What does this figure to the left look
like? A cube. But is there really a cube
over here?
Is there a real cube?
No. Just lots of Pac-Man like patterns,
right? Or this figure, the second
figure. What do you see?
You see a dog, but is there a dog?
Not really. Right. The one to the
extreme right. This is the one that's
most fun. What do you guys see in this
picture? To the very right
over here,
the figure to the extreme right. What do
you see? A virus.
It looks like a ball with spikes, right?
But there is no ball. It's just a bunch
of conical looking triangles and your
brain filled up these the rest of the
pattern to give you a larger to make you
think you saw some a more complete
concept. So this is what is called
gestalt which represents the brain's in
tendency to organize disconnected bits
into whole objects. So a lot of early
research went into
understanding things like gestalt. But
why does gestalt happen? How does the
brain actually process images? There
wasn't a lot of work on this until these
two guys Hubel and Visa in 1959. They
had this first study on the neural
correlates of vision called the
receptive fields in capstri cortex. Now
the human brain is a classic example of
why we are not the product of
intelligent design. Now, if you were to
build a robot which had an uh a visual
system, you'd have a lens. Right behind
the lens, you would have a sensor.
Behind the sensor, you'd have a you have
all the wires that capture the
information from the uh sensor. And
these wires would go into some
processing unit immediately after it and
subsequent processing would come later.
Our
visual system is backwards.
We have a lens. Then we have all the
wires that uh carry information. Then we
have the sensor which means that these
wires have to punch a hole through the
sensor which is your retina which gives
you a blind spot in your vision. And
then you have the skull. But then this
goes all the way to the back of the
brain and it gets processed out here.
And then afterwards further processing
happens back inward. So this is not how
I or you would design things but that's
how nature has designed our visual
system. And this portion of the brain
that processes the initial responses
from the retina is what is called the V1
cortex in the human visual system. And
the equivalent in cats is the stride
cortex called the stride cortex because
the neurons look strided.
So uh Hubel and Visel set out to study
this right cortex and to do this they
used 24 cats anesthetized immobilized
they were put on artificial respirators
they were anesthetized with truth serum
so they could tell no lies and then
electrodes were stuck into the stride
cortex. They didn't tell us if the cats
survived the experiment. They probably
looked like these. But then they tell us
that the brain tissue was studied later.
So they leave the rest of our
imagination.
Anyway, what did they study? They would
keep the cat's eyes open forcibly
and beam light patterns onto the uh into
the eye. So, they stuck electrodes into
uh individual cells in the stride cortex
and saw how it responded.
Now the way they would do it they had a
pinpoint and they would move this in
different directions up and down this
way this way this way and so on and this
way this light itself would have
different wavelengths and they would see
how the brain responded the how the cell
responded to the movements of the light
and here's what they found. First, your
retina is a pretty large region, but an
individual cell only connects to a small
region in the retina. This is what is
called the receptive field of the cell.
Within the so anything that happens in
the rest of the retina does not cause
any response over here. But within this
region, they found something
interesting. There were regions where if
you beam the light then regardless of
what else happened the cell would simply
not fire. So these were inhibitory
regions and then you had other regions
where if there was no light in the
inhibitory regions and light in these
regions then the cell would fire and the
kinds of patterns they found were
something like these. They found that
the combination of the inhibitory and
excitatory regions ended up looking like
oriented lines like this guy. This cell
responds to light patterns in this
direction. This cell responds to light
patterns in this direction. This cell
responds to linear light patterns in
this direction. So each of these cells,
it turned out, ended up being responsive
to oriented
uh patterns of light.
And so here's a typical experiment. They
were for responses from a single cell.
If they move the light pattern left to
right, the cell did not respond. As they
keep increasing the angle, when it
becomes vertical, you can see a lot of
spikes. As the light keeps rotating,
when it becomes horizontal again, the
spikes stop. It doesn't matter if the
movement of the light is fully extended
like this or just a half beam, you get
the same kind of response. So this
particular neuron we see is responsive
to vertical bands of light. Different
neurons were responsive to bands
oriented in different directions. So
oriented slits of light were found to be
the most effective stimula for
activating the stri cortex neurons. In a
later paper they showed that within the
stride cortex they actually have two
levels of processing. So they call these
two levels of processing which are
associated with two different cell
types. The simple or S cells and the
complex or C cells. Both the S cells and
the C cells responded to oriented splits
of light. But complex cells tended not
to be confused by random noise while the
simple cells could be confused. How
exactly did they operate? Now it turns
out that if you look at a individual
cell on the retina, the individual
sensor is responsive to a somewhat
circular pattern of light. So the S cell
ended up being responsive to patterns of
cells on the retina that were oriented
along lines. And that's why the S cells
were responsive to oriented slits of
light. But then these guys could
actually get confused by little bits of
light here and there. So the C cell now
looks at a collection of S cells and
then picks up the strongest response of
these S cells. Which means that if you
have three different S cells and they're
all firing, if it picks up only the
strongest one, these two guys are
probably just being excited by some
noise or or otherwise uh uh made to fire
by irrelevant patterns and so you end up
cleaning up the response of the uh S
cells. So once again, the simpler S
cells responded to respond to oriented
slits of light and the complex or C
cells clean up their response by picking
the largest of a small collection of S
cells that they connected to. Moreover,
they also found that this whole thing
had a pattern of buildup. So you would
have some S cells. These S cells would
be cleaned up by C cells. Then you'd
have another set of S cells which looked
at these C cells and their responses
were cleaned up by more C cells and so
on. And as you got deeper into this uh
hierarchy while these initial guys
responded to oriented slits of light as
you went in the patterns this that the
cells responded to became more and more
complex. Then later on they demonstrated
even more complex responses and this
time they were waking worked on waking
macak monkeys and at that point my
willingness to read this research
stopped. So uh yeah and just to make
things worse uh they also add in adding
insult to injury they say however this
model cannot accommodate color spatial
frequency and many other features
features to neurons are tuned the exact
organization of all these cortical
columns within V1 remains a hot topic of
current research so it's not really
clear how much they discovered but this
did lead to our current models of uh
computer vision which leads us to our
Very first. Oh.
10 seconds, guys.
Okay, let me end this poll here.
What is the answer?
What's the answer, guys? One, right?
Sells find the pattern. Cells clean them
up. Good. So, that's in 1959, early 60s.
Fast forward uh 20 years to this guy
Konohiko Fukushima.
He recognized deficiencies in the Hub
Visel model. One of the things that the
hub and visel model didn't address is
position invariance of the input. How
many of you guys So Jesse SLs respond to
patterns? Cells clean up the responses
by uh by picking the largest of small
groups of cells. So, how many of you
guys have heard of the Jennifer Aniston
neuron?
Anybody heard of it?
The Jennifer Aniston neuron.
That's a famous story. There was a paper
in nature about it. It turns out that
when people have epilepsy, uh they are
uh the a lot of epileptic patients have
lesions in the brain and so they end up
in the hospital
where they open up the skull and try to
fix the lesions. And while this is
happening, they're lying there in the
hospital with their brains opened up for
the world to see. And that's when uh
scientists who work on perception and uh
and uh neuroscientists
have a field day. They come and put
little uh collections of sensors on
these cells and then show these poor
patients different things and they can
measure the responses of the cells that
are exposed. And they found that on one
particular patient there was a cell that
only responded when this guy was shown
pictures of Jennifer Aniston. So this is
the famous Jennifer Aniston mural. Now
there's nothing special about Jennifer
Aniston. It turns out that he has
specific cells for different people
including your grandmother. So this is
what we call the grandmother cell. The
key thing is this grandmother assemble
will fire.
If your grandma is in your field of
vision, regardless of whether she's to
the far right or to the far left or in
the center, a mere presence in your
field of vision makes the cell fire. So
this cell is position invariant and
that's something the hub and visel model
did not capture. So Fukushima came up
with the first computational model built
on the hub hub and visel model study.
And so in his computational model you
had
layers of neurons and within each layer
you had a pair an S a set of S cells and
a set of C cells. So this formed one
block and you had a chain of such
blocks.
Now within each block the S cells, there
were lots of S cells and there were lots
of C cells. Only the S cells were
plastic, meaning they could learn their
responses. The response of the C cell
was fixed. Furthermore, the S cells were
organized in a very specific way and the
way they were organized was as follows.
they within
what they call the S plane. So within
each block you had a set of S cells and
C cells and these S cells were organized
in planes. So with this set of this
entire set would be one such clean over
here within which you'd have many of
these subplanes and within each
subplanes you had many neurons. Every
one of these neurons had exactly the
same response within each block. The
different blocks had neurons with
different responses, but within each
block, all the neurons had exactly the
same response. The difference was in the
region of the input that they looked at.
So if you had an input, this guy might
look at this region. This guy might look
at an adjacent region and so on. So
between all of these guys, they
inspected the entire input. Since every
one of them were identical, if the
pattern that they were looking for
occurred anywhere in this picture, one
of these neurons would fire. And each of
these
in the splane was looking for a uh had a
different neuron set of or a different
collection of identical neurons each
looking for a different pattern. So
these C planes also had many neurons and
they were also arranged in these little
rectangular patterns except that now
these guys
cleaned up the response of the S cells.
Each point over here looks looked at a
small region in the S corresponding S
plane and just picked up and gave you a
response that depended on all of these.
So in some sense they were they were
cleaning things up. The region that each
of these cells was looking on looking at
in Fukushima's original model was
elliptical.
So how did the whole thing work? The
very first layer of SNC cells operated
like this. This would be your retina and
in in with within the first layer S
cells which are again organized into a
bunch of planes. Within each plane you
had several cells which were looking at
the retina. each of them looking at an
elliptical region of of a different
position at a different position of the
retina. So then subsequently you had the
C cell planes where each C cell
responded to a bunch of uh S cells in
the corresponding S cell plane. So this
was one block. Then following this there
was a second block of S and C cells.
These S cells were also again organized
in a bunch of planes. But now each S
cell over here looked not just at an
elliptical region of the of the
corresponding of the of a C plane in the
previous layer but looked at the same
region in all the C planes of the
previous layer. So this guy responds to
all of these. So also each cell over
here would be looking at the same
identical elliptical region for in all
of these planes. So these are now these
SLs are searching for patterns except
they're considering the output of all of
these C planes. They're trying to detect
the patterns and the search for the
patterns is position invariant because
all of these S cells have identical
responses and then once again you have C
planes which clean up these SL responses
by operating on little elliptical
regions and coming up with a consensus
response that is more robust to noise.
So you had many such groups of SNC cells
operating on the input. Did this whole
thing make sense?
This organization over here.
Did you guys make did this make sense?
Okay. And not only did they do that did
did Fukushima come up with this model,
he even came up with a mathematical
model for it. How did the S cells
respond? The each S cell was looking at
elliptical regions from all the C planes
in the previous layer. And these values
were combined using a formula where the
formula also included some weights
which were learnable. And this was the
response of the SL. It's a very ugly
formula. I'm not entirely sure how we
came how we came up with it. But if you
look really closely at it, it just looks
like a reloop operating on an alphine
combination of these inputs. the C
cells. Once again, we're looking at a
combination of a set of S cell outputs.
And the specific function that he used
to combine all of these responses was
this ugly function over here. But then
once again, if you look at this C cell
uh response closely enough, it ends up
looking a lot like a max.
So you can simply replace these strange
functions with a reloop operating on an
aphine function of the inputs and a max
and so that gives us the entire network.
Now when you so when this network
operates on any input as you go deeper
into the network the first layer S and C
cell SC block would have a small number
of S plananes because the C cells are
looking at groups of in of S cells the C
planes are smaller than the S planes
they are they are sort of combining
entire regions of the SL S plane into a
single point over here. So the C planes
would be smaller than the S planes. When
you get to the next block, the number of
S planes over here would be greater than
the number of S planes over here. And
each of these S planes would be looking
at all of these C planes to form their
patterns. They would in turn be cleaned
up by the their own C cells to get a
bunch of C planes. And then in the next
block, you would have even more S cells,
S plananes, which would be operating on
these guys and so on. So as you go
deeper and deeper into the network uh
the planes the number of planes keeps
increasing.
Fukushima also came up with a way of
training these models and the way he did
it remember again only the S cells are
trained. So you have within any within
any S layer you have all of these planes
and all of these cells are identical
right they're all looking at the
corresponding C cell planes from the
previous layer. So uh he would just look
at he performed simple Hebian learning
within each splane he found which
cell responded most strongly and then he
would use hepian learning to update all
of these weights and then once he
updated the weight for this guy he would
copy those weights to all the other
cells in the plane since you'd have a
different point in each of the cells
Eventually
all of these S cells would get learned
and then of course the C cell has no
learning. So he trained this on a bunch
of digits
and the whole training is unsupervised.
There's no label, right? He just trains
it on a bunch of digits. The S cells are
being learned on using Hebian learning.
The C cells have a fixed response. When
he trained it, he found that the early
layers S cells in the early layers learn
to respond to oriented lines. As you go
deeper and deeper into the network, the
S cells respond to more and more complex
patterns and eventually at the deepest
look uh layer the patterns that the S
cells and C cells respond to end up
being entire semantic categories.
So it's effectively it's unsupervised.
So effectively you're just performing
clustering. And when he trained it on
digits or characters, he found that in
the final layer, each of the C cells
ended up responding to one category of
input. For example, once once one uh set
of C cells would respond to the digit
zero, the other to the digit one and so
on. It has been not been given these
labels. It just automatically learns to
do so. And it also tends to be very
robust to changes in position, small
bits of noise and so on. So Fukushima's
model successfully learns to cluster
semantic visual concepts
even in noise but it's unsupervised.
So
uh here is our second
10 seconds, guys.
Okay, let me end this one.
What's the answer to the first question,
guys?
Second one.
True. True. Okay. If both of them are
true, how would you add supervision to
Fukushima's model? Anybody?
So, Fukushima's model, by the way, was
called the Neocognitron.
The fact that it's got the word Neo
means that it's probably the last in a
series of models all with the word
cognitron in it. I'm guessing how would
you assign uh supervision? I think add
supervision to this. Anyone
a suggestion?
How would you add supervision to it?
One guess
add labels
labels where right loss function and
labels but there's something else
missing right what is missing
what's missing
backdrop
these are just features you're going to
have to add a softmax
classification layer right yes or
Right? And once you add a classification
layer, you can provide labels and voila,
you have a supervised model. And so that
is in fact what
Yan Leon did. The neocetron is fully
supervised. Semantic labels are
automatically built. Can we add external
supervision? Yes. And there were many
proposals. So for in in a long time you
had temporal correlation included by
Hama Atlas and Marx by Kevin Lang at CNO
and of course in images convolutional
neural networks which was uh uh
implemented by Yan Leon that's what he
won his turing award for. So what Yan
Leon did was just to add a little uh
softmax. He actually added an entire
neural network out here which outputed
output class labels and then you of
course have the ground truth labels you
can use back prop to train the entire
network. But then there are a few
engineering solutions you can uh you can
make. So first uh we have engineering u
optimizations. First, we know that
within each plane, all of the cells have
the same response, which means anytime
you update one of the cells, you have to
update the weights for all of these
cells. Uh, other than that,
instead of having so many copies of the
cell, you can just think of it as one
cell scanning the input and uh that one
cell scanning the input to produce this
output. And that's mathematically
strictly equivalent. So uh this is
basically what Yan Leon did. Again the
original neo cognitron uses many
identical copies of each neuron within
each splane rather than having many
identical copies. Yan's work used a
single copy to scan the input. It's
mathematically equivalent.
So here's the overall uh model. Now in
Fukushima's model the uh receptive field
for each neuron was elliptical. That's
kind of tough to deal with. So Yan
cleaned it up. He said I'll make it
rectangular. Makes it much simpler,
right? So the receptive fields of S
cells were now actually square. And the
C cells again also had elliptical
receptive fields. And so the ele the
receptive field of the receptive field
is the region of the input that the cell
is looking at as we saw earlier. Right?
So this two was made square. Then uh
instead of having a onetoone
correspondence between the cells here
and over here the sea cells actually
stroed. So if this guy was looking at a
region the next guy was looking at a
region which may which would have
minimal overlap with the first region.
So the sea cells became C the uh the C
planes became smaller than the S planes
as you got through the network.
So effectively this caused a
downsampling of the maps and furthermore
instead of the complex function that
Fukushima had he replaced the uh
computation to be very simple. The S
cells
computed an aphine function of all of
these regions which are squared as I
said and then applied a sigmoid
activation to it. The C cells simply
performed a max on all of the cells that
all of the elements that they were
looking at. So everything was
simplified.
And with that done
now here is the overall model. Again SLS
they are just using simple sigmoid act
sigmoid activation perceptrons which
operate on all of the input planes and
instead of having many copies of the
cell you're scanning the C cells are
looking at a square region of the S
plane and picking the largest value.
Then the final output over here is
passed through a neural network in this
case with a softmax to produce output
labels which can be performed compared
to ground truth and then you can perform
back propagation and the only parameters
you'd learn are the parameters of the SS
and here is the CNN that uh uh here is
the output of the CNN that Yan Neman
built back in the day. This was lit
five. So I'm assuming he had built linet
1 2 3 and four before that.
And this was applied applied to m the
mnest digits. Now in those days people
still sent postal mail and the post
office had this problem. They had to
recognize the addresses on these
envelopes. Doing it manually was a bit
challenging. So they wanted an automated
mechanism to do that. And the guys at
AT&T set about building a tool for this.
The Yan Leon CNN
was uh one of the tools designed to
recognize handwritten digits so that you
could read them off envelopes and the
MNEST corpus consists entirely of
handwritten digits.
Layet ended up being really really uh
being really really robust. So
the story so far the mamalian visual
cortex consists of S cells which capture
oriented visual patterns and C cells
which perform a majority vote over
groups of S cells for robustness to
noise and positional jitter.
Fukushima's neoron
emulates this behavior with planar banks
of S and C cells with identical response
to enable shift and variance. Only the S
cells are learned. C cells perform the
equivalent of a max of groups of S cells
for robustness. Unsupervised learning
results in learning useful semantic
patterns. Yan Leon's lanet added
external supervision to the neo
cognitron. So the S planes of cells with
identical response were now modeled by a
scan which is a convolution over the
image planes in the previous layer. C
planes are emulated by cells that
perform a max over groups of SL outputs,
reducing the size of the S planes. This
whole thing gave us a convolutional
neural network. We'll go into all of the
computation in some detail, but did all
of this make sense so far at a very high
level?
Yes. Is good, no, right? Because we'll
go into this detail detail, right? So,
here is the general architecture of the
convolutional neural network. It
consists of convolutional layers
corresponding to S plananes and pooling
layers corresponding to C planes. The
you can have any number of convolutional
layers and any number of cooling layers.
Typically they would al occur
alternately but you can have sequences
of convolutional layers before you have
a pooling there. Then the final layer of
the slot has a bunch of values which are
then flattened into a vector and then
passed into a multi-layer perceptron
which computes the final output. This is
the general architecture of the
convolutional neural network. So this
making sense
right this picture. Yeah. Yes or no?
Okay. Only the convolutional layers and
the final MLP are learnable. the pooling
layers are not.
So let's go into see how these things
actually operate. What exactly is a
convolutional layer? I just kind of hand
wave my way around it. But then let's
look into it carefully and look at the
computation. A convolutional layer
consists of a series of maps. These
rectangular planes they correspond to
the S planes in the neoron. They're
variously also called feature maps or
activation maps. But then
uh Christian just wait for me right
we'll get there right. So how does so
within any s layer I have a bunch of s
planes right or maps let's consider one
map this map is computed from all of the
maps of the previous layer. So this guy
is going to use all of these guys to
compute its value. And within this map
you have two layer two operations. First
you compute an aphine value to get you
an aphine map and then corresponding to
this aphine map is a learnable filter
which represent the weights of the uh
neurons.
Subsequently you apply an activation
function on all of these aphine values
to get the activation map. So is this
picture making sense? What happens
within each of these maps?
Yes or no? I see one. Yes.
Okay. So, assuming it makes sense, let's
see how this computation is done.
I'm going to again observe that all of
the maps in the previous layer
contribute to this guy. Right? So,
instead of looking at all of the maps,
let's just look at how just one of these
maps contributes to contributes to this
one. Okay?
So I'm going to draw a picture. This
green p figure represents one of these
maps. Not all of them, just one of these
maps. Now to compute any particular
value, this slane will have a filter
which is which has some
squared shape and the values within the
filter are the weights of the filter.
Because it's a neuron, it can also have
a bias. In my example, all of the values
within this previous plane are binary
and all the filter values are also
binary. This is just for illustration.
And then you're going to scan this guy
to compute this map. How so? You place
this filter on the top left corner. So
the little red line numbers over here
show the filter values. The big numbers
show the actual uh underlying value of
the underlying map. And then when you
place the filter on the top left corner,
each weight is multiplied by the
corresponding
uh input value and the whole thing is
summed up. So here it's going to be 1 *
1 + 1 * 0 + 1 * 1 + 0 * 0 + 1 * 1 + 1 *
0 + 0 * 1 + 0 * 0 + 1 * 1. That ends up
being four. So you enter the four over
here and then you step forward one step
at a time and repeat the same operation
at each point to fill up this map. This
computation makes sense
to all of you guys, right? Very easy,
right? except that that that only showed
you how this guy was a how this guy was
what what the contribution to this guy
was from one of these maps. In reality,
all of the maps in the previous layer
are contributing to it. So corresponding
to each one of these planes the you will
have a filter but the filter itself is
going to have as many planes what we
also call channels as the number of
input maps which are also called
channels right so Bruno we'll get there
right
and so here I just showed you one clean
of the filter one channel of the filter
but the filter is going to have as many
channels as input maps
And all the channels are going to be
different. So the as the color code
shows, no two numbers are required to be
identical. They can all be different.
And now to compute this map, this output
map. So this guy here represents the
input map. This represents the filter
with which this output map also shown by
this guy here is going to be computed.
And now the filter would be placed here.
and you would perform a weighted you the
filter these colors represent weights.
So at each position you're going to
multiply the underlying map value with
the corresponding filter value. So you
get nine terms from here, nine from here
and nine from here. You'd sum all 27 to
get this one guy.
This picture makes sense.
Yes or no?
Right. Okay.
And so then
you'd step forward and repeat the same
operation and next get the next guy.
Step forward, repeat the same operation
and get the next guy. And you keep
performing this computation left to
right, top to bottom to fill out this
output map. Did this computation make
sense to everybody,
right? So here is the arithmetic.
This the this W represents the filter,
right?
And the filter is going to so one here
just represents the layer number in my
example.
L so M over here is going to represent
this guy. We have M= 1 in my example. If
you ignore the dots, M goes from 1 2 3.
Then K represents the height of the
filter and L represents the width of the
filter. So within each guy at each
position, you're summing over this 3 +
3. And what you're summing is the weight
times the underlying MAC value, right?
And you do this across all of the guys.
So that's the sum over n. And that's
plus and of course it's a neuron, so you
may have a bias typically at zero. And
that entire operation is going to give
you the output at one location. That
make sense to everybody?
Right? So the number of filters, no the
number of channels in the filter is
going to be the number of maps in the
previous layer. If I want to compute a
second output map, I would have a second
filter which is going to be entirely
different from the first filter. Philip,
that answer question.
Yes. No. Right. The B is the bias.
Remember the filter is just a neuron,
right? So the B is outside the
summation.
So did this make sense to all of you
guys?
Yes or no?
The filters
the filters will be learned. We'll get
to that, right? Okay. And so the second
filter will do the same thing and it
will generate the second one. There's a
different way of looking at it. Instead
of drawing them all one below the other,
I can stack all of these input maps up
like so into a cuboid. And then the
filter itself, I can stack all of the
channels of the filter into a cuboid
also like so. And so this is the set of
input maps. And this is the filter.
Is this illustration making sense? I
just collapse them into a cuboid
to everybody? Okay. And then what do I
do? I place this cuboid in this top left
corner and I do an element wise product
of the terms within the cuboid which are
the weights and the underlying map and
then sum over all of them. So this
operation over here, this guy here
represents
the summation within one map. And then
this guy here,
the second one represents the summation
across all maps. And that's going to
give me the output value at one
location.
This make sense to everybody
what we just did?
And we just keep doing this to fill out
the entire map. And that's how the
entire convolution operation is
performed. So
what are the K stack input map? Are they
different images of different numbers?
No, they are they are okay, we'll get to
that, right? So
that you have to worry about the size.
Someone asked about the size. What is
the size of the input? What is the size
of the filter? What's the size of the
output? The size of the output may not
be identical to the size of the input.
So let let's take a look here. My input
was 5 + 5. The filter was 3 + 3. What is
the size of the output going to be?
Anybody?
What is the size of the output? It's
going to be 3 + 3. Why? Because I have
one position over here and I have two
steps that I can take. Right? So the
input is generally of width n and the
filter is of width n. What is the size
of the output going to be?
Anybody?
What's the size of the output going to
be?
You're going to have one when you place
it in the top left corner. One plus the
number of steps you're going to take is
going to be n minus m. Right?
These are the remaining steps you can
take. So it's going to be 1 + n - m and
that's going to be 1 + m nus m on each
side. That answer that clear to
1 1 + 1. Yeah. So that this makes sense
to everybody. 1 + 1 will not reduce
anything at all. Right? So
okay. So that's going to be the size of
the output.
And so for the image size is n cross m
the filter is n cross m the output is
going to be n minus m + one on each
side.
So
which features this is the filter
jambaro
and your you're scanning when you scan
there are only three steps you can take
that's about it right
so the convolution size if the image is
n cross n the filter is m cross m each
side is going to be n minus n + one this
results in a reduction in the size of
the output because what went in was m
but the size reduced by m minus one.
So the output is not going to be the
same size as the input. This make sense
to everybody?
Yes or no?
So what can you do if you want the
output to be the same size as the input?
What can you do? Anyone?
How would you make the output the same
size as the input? You can just add
zeros all around, right? And how many
rows of how many z rows of zeros would
you add?
How many rows of zeros would you add?
Anyone?
If your filter size is m, you're losing
mus1 rows and n minus one columns.
Correct?
That's what we saw. So, you're going to
add m -1 / 2 columns of zeros here, n
minus one over two columns of zeros
here, n minus one over two columns of
rows of zeros here, and n minus one over
two rows of zeros here. The resultant is
going to be of size n + m minus one
after padding and then if you if it
shrinks by m minus one afterwards the
result is going to have the same size as
the in this make sense to everybody
right okay and so that only gave us this
aine map subsequently
every element you apply an activation
function to every element to compute the
output activation map. So here is the
overall operation. You're scanning left
to right, top to bottom. At each
position, you have this cuboid. This is
a cuboid. It's a 3D tensor. You compute
an inner product with your filter, which
is also a 3D tensor. And you may add a
bias to it. And then you to get the
aphine value, and then you apply an
activation to it to get the activation
map. This is in each layer. The next
layer is going to operate on the Y's
from the previous layer. So this makes
sense to everybody.
Yes or no?
This code makes sense to everyone. Okay,
give me a few thumbs ups, guys. I'm
seeing like a very anemic five or 10
thumbs ups and I'm just going to chug
on, but I'd like to see some response.
So the convolution summary, convolution
layers scan the input using a bank of
filters. A filter is just a neuron in a
scanning layer. Each filter jointly
scans all the maps in the previous layer
to produce an output map. And there are
as many output maps as filters. One
output map per filter. So going back
over here when we said this, this filter
produced
this filter produced
this map.
This filter
produced
this map. You're going to have one
filter for every output map. And the
filter is going to have as many channels
as the number of input maps.
The number of filters as the number of
output maps. The number of channels in
the filter is the number of input maps.
That that clear to everybody?
Yes. No.
And that becomes more obvious when you
actually see this in the cuboid uh
model. Okay. Uh then we may also have to
pad the edges of the input maps to
ensure that the outputs are the same
size as the input maps. Otherwise
convolution loses rows and columns on
the edges of the scan.
the other component and so have we all
understood what happens over here
in a convolution layer. I have a certain
number of
maps over here. How does this number of
maps relate to the number of filters?
I have a certain number of maps. How
does the number of maps relate to the
number of filters? Anyone?
The number of maps is the same as the
number of filters. Now, each map over
here operates on a bunch of maps, input
maps. How does the number of maps over
here relate to the number of channels in
the filter
over here
also the same right? So, if you only
allow for three steps,
okay? Yes, John, you'll have some edge
effects. So, now let's look at the
second component. pooling. What is
pooling? Now remember that we mentioned
that when I'm going to operate on a
region, I'm trying to compute complex
structures from lower level complex uh
detect complex patterns from simpler
patterns. So I might want to detect that
there was a there was a uh let me change
it choose a different color that there
was a there was a petal over here. There
was there was the central uh uh stamman
here and there was a petal over here.
This could be a combination. But if this
petal shifted a little bit, would that
change the pattern entirely
or would it do you still expect it to be
part of a flower? If this petal shifted
a little bit, would you still expect it
to be part of a flower or is it going to
So guys, here's my question.
If I have a new a second layer neuron
which is looking at first layer outputs
and and one one map in the first layer
detects pedals of this kind, the other
detects pedals of this kind, the third
detects these statements, then the
second layer neuron could be detecting
patterns of this kind. Right? If the
petal over here jittered a little bit,
would it completely destroy the pattern
or would it still be the same pattern?
What do you guys think? It would still
be the same pattern, right? So, you need
to account for that. How do we account
for that? Through max pooling. Max
pooling looks at little regions of the
input and just copies the largest value
over. So, it might be looking at this
these four values, copying the largest.
Here it is six. Then it's going to
stride, copies the largest in that
window. Then copies the largest in that
window and keeps doing that left to
right, top to bottom until it has uh
included until it has scanned the entire
input map. Does this making sense? Max
pulling.
So how does the largest help? Meaning it
just says that it's not so much the
largest as the fact that it the six
means that a petal was found.
It doesn't matter where it was found. So
you're adding some jitter invariance
within this region.
That answer.
And how are these values calculated?
These are these are the outputs of your
convolution, right? Convolution. These
are the activation map. These values are
already there. Max pooling is operating
on these guys. The answer
right. Okay. So moving on. Right. So
that's max pooling. Here's what happens.
The max pooling, you're going to look
over a window and for max pooling, you'd
find the index, the location of the
largest value, store it, and then copy
the value at that location into the
output. The reason we do this in a
two-step manner where you first find the
location and then copy it is for to
enable back propagation later in the
proceedings when we're training the
model. You can also replace the max by
the mean. You can say instead of just
picking the largest I take the average
and in that case you'll be picking the
mean of these four guys and then
scanning. So here instead of finding the
index of the largest and then copying
the value over you'll be taking the mean
of the window. This is mean pulling.
There's a difference between max and
mean pulling clear to you guys.
This is max pooling. We pick the largest
and mean pull line. We pick copy the
mean. Right?
So
pooling layers scan the input using a
pooling operation. Eg selecting the max
from a k cross k block of input. Each
pooling filter scans the individual maps
of the previous layer to produce an
output pulled map. You know, and
uh so
literally just you copy it over and
create a new map. This is the input of
the pooling. This is the output of the
pooling unit.
That answer your question,
right? Eva, did that answer your
question? Okay.
Max and moon are different mean are
different design choices. So each
pooling filter scans the individual maps
in the previous layer to produce an
output pool map. So you have as many
output maps as input maps. For pooling,
we do not generally pad the edges
because if you pad them, the zeros will
result in bogus pool values on the
boundless.
So, we've considered convolution layers
and pooling layers. Have
did you get an idea of how all of these
guys work? The con layers and the
pooling layers.
Yes. No. Right. The pictures was Can I
see some thumbs ups maybe?
like 8:30 per.
So let me move on. There's another there
are two other operations which are very
important. One is called down sampling.
A down sampling layer simply drops S
minus one of every S rows and S minus
one rows of column of every S columns to
reduce the size of the map. So if this
was the input map and you down sample by
a factor of two, you just drop every
second row and every second column shown
by these black regions and only retain
the remaining. This is down sampling.
This make sense to everybody?
Downsampling.
Very easy, right? So here's what you
would do. You would literally, this is
pseudo code for it. just take a stride
and just copy the position in the new at
the new location. Now in practice you
don't have separate downsampling layers.
Down sampling is generally combined with
the layers before it. So if you have a
convolution layer followed by
downsampling, you combine them into a
convolution with stride. If you have a
pooling layer followed by downsampling,
you combine them into a pooling pooling
with a stride. So uh how does that
happen? Right? If I want to perform a
convolution followed by a downsampling
by a factor of two, instead of
performing the full convolution and then
computing the output while convolving
each time I take a step both in the left
to right direction and the top to bottom
direction, I'd shift by two to compute
the output and that's going to reduce
the size of the output.
This make sense to everybody
what we just did. Right?
So
for an input of n cross n and filters of
n cross m let's try s. If you down
sample of the convolution the size is
going to be n minus m / s + one. Okay.
So literally in your pseudo code you
just include a stride. I just two was
just an example I g same thing with
pooling right now. We'll get to that.
Okay. Uh
so
uh when you're pooling, same thing. If
you follow a pooling with a down
sampling layer, you just perform pooling
with down sampling. Same thing if you're
performing max pooling with a down
sampling of two. Instead, you're going
to perform max pooling with a stride of
two as one operation. You pick the max
here, then the max here, then the max
here, and the max here to get the
output. So did this make sense? Max
cooling with pooling with stride.
Yes. No.
So downsampling is actually a separate
operation which you should always think
of it as a separate operation. But in
practically speaking, you combine it
with a previous layer and perform the
previous operation with a stride. That's
all you do. Right? So this is max
pooling. With down sampling, you just
have a stride. Same thing with mean
pooling. you'll be striding by two and
the outcome is that uh at each after
each mean operation you're going to be
stepping by two both left to right and
top to bottom two is just an example the
stride is a design choice right so
now anytime you're performing down
sampling if the input is n cross n and
even for pooling if the pooling filter
is p cross p and the stride is d then
the size of the output is going to be n
minus p / d + one. And for pooling you
typically do not zero pad because in
pooling if you just introduce zeros on
the edges the zeros are going to uh the
zeros could overwhelm some of the values
inside and you'd end up losing
information. You only pad for uh
convolutions. The reverse of down
sampling is something called the
upsampling layer. and upsampling or
dilation layer simply introduces sus one
rows and columns of zeros
between adjacent rows and columns. So if
I want to upsample this image by a
factor of two this map I'm just going to
add a a column of zeros between every
two columns and a row of zeros between
every two rows. This is going to result
in an increase in the size of the map by
a factor of s. So uh is this making
sense? Upsampling.
This does this make sense to all of you
guys? Right. Okay.
An upsampling layer is usually perfor
followed by a convolutional layer. It
doesn't make sense to follow an
upsampling layer with a pooling layer
because the pooling layer will simply
pick up all the zeros and you will lose
information.
And it's also not useful as the final
layer of a CNN because just introducing
a bunch of zeros doesn't really do
anything for you. Upsampling is
generally followed by convolution. It's
they also call it convolution with a
stride uh convolution with a fractional
stride and the intention is to increase
the size of the maps. I have pseudo code
for it. I'll skip it. Right? So
if you want to upsample you would
introduce some zeros but then typically
it's followed by a convolution and so
that convolution now is going to have uh
the output of the convolution is going
to be larger than the input. So this is
how this is generally called
convolution with a fractional stride. So
if you want to upsample by a factor s
this is this is the same as striding by
a factor 1 / s. You don't actually have
a fractional strike. What you actually
do is upsample and then convolve. So, is
this making sense?
Yes or no?
Did upsampling make sense to you guys?
Okay.
All right.
So, moving on. Resampling summary map
sizes can be changed down sampling or
upsampling. In down sampling, you drop S
minus one of S rows and columns. In
upsampling, you insert SUS one rows
between every two rows and columns. Down
sampling typically follows convolution
or pooling. It reduces the size of the
maps. Upsampling occurs before
convolution and increases the size of
the map. It does not generally occur
before pooling layers.
So the study so far convolutional neural
networks are supervised versions of the
of a computational model of mealian
vision. They include convolutional
layers comprising learned filters that
scan the outputs of the previous layer
and pooling layers that load over groups
of outputs from the convolution layer.
Convolution can change the size of the
output. This can be controlled via zero
padding because of edge effects. You can
you can the output can be smaller than
the input. If you don't want to lose the
lose size, you would zero pad. Pooling
layers may perform max mean or different
porms which are on the slides. Pooling
layers could even be learned. We haven't
I haven't discussed it in the class but
it's on the slide. Resampling layers
increase or decrease the size of the
map. Down sampling can be merged with a
preceding operation simply by striding
with a scanning with a stride greater
than one. Up samp sampling must always
occur before convolution operations. Any
questions? Is all of this clear before I
proceed? Any questions?
Okay. Is all of this clear? Give me a
yes or no. everything that we've done so
far.
You can wait for some 25 thumbs ups
before I move on. So, please be
enthusiastic with your thumbs ups.
All righty.
So, is there a way you just have fewer
filters and you reduce the number of
channels? That's it, right? The number
of channels is equal to output channels
equals the number of filters.
How does a pooling layer go into pooling
and convolution layers are entirely
different.
Okay, so
uh let's move on. Here's the third poll.
10 seconds, guys.
Okay, give me five more.
All right. So
for the first question,
which are the true statements? For the
first question,
one and three. For the second one,
which are the true statements? Two and
four.
So upsampling by S introduces S minus
one zeros between adjacent rows and
commons. They are generally followed by
convolution layers. Downsampling by S
deletes S minus one consecutive rows and
columns and retains every only every S
throughout column.
These are usually merged with the
convolution uping days before them which
are modified to perform convolutional
pooling with a strat.
So let's put everything together in a
typical image classification task.
I'm going to assume max pooling images.
Say let's say I wanted to classify this
image. If I were given a color image, a
color image is not just a color image.
It's got three different images in it.
It's got the R, the G, and the B
channels. The reason we began using the
term channels for these maps comes from
images where the colors are generally
called channels. So a color image of
this kind has an R channel, a G channel,
and a B B channel.
So the input is now three pictures.
We can stack them up into a cube. So is
this making sense? My input to the to
the whole process. Did that make sense
to everybody? Okay. So now if I want my
first layer is a convolutional layer.
How many channels will the filters have
for my convolution layer? In this
example, how many channel what is the
shape of my filter and how many how many
channels will it have?
The filter is going to be a cuboid,
right, with a phase. And it's going to
have three channels. Three channels
because one for the R, one for the G,
and one for the B, right? And so
I'm going to have K1 total filters. Each
will have some phase L cross L and three
channels.
The size typically is a power of two
like 2 + 2, 4 + 4. the the number of
filters is typically a power of two like
two filters, four filters, eight
filters, 16 filters, 32. We'll get to Y
in in a little while. And filters are
typically 5 + 5, 3 + 3, or even 1 + 1.
The smaller the filter, the smaller the
scale of the feature it captures.
But then if it gets to be too small,
you're not really looking at spatial
extent. So, and what is uh so you want
them to be small enough to capture fine
features, particularly important if
you're scaling down images.
And what is a 1 + one filter? What do
you think a 1 + one filter is?
Anyone
have we encountered 1 + one filters in
the previous class?
Did we encounter a 1 + 1 filter in the
previous class?
A 1 + one filter is just going to be
taking a weighted combination of these
three guys. This was the nondistributed
scan. Remember we were speaking of
distributed scans and non-distributed
scans. If you had a distributed scan,
then the next layer neurons were looking
at regions in the previous input. In the
nondistributed scan, they were looking
at just one element of the previous
layer outputs. Remember, remember that
yes or no?
Right? And so 1 + one is basically a
nondistributed scan. That's all it is.
And you can combine distributed and
non-distributed scans in your CNN.
That make sense to everybody?
Everyone? Okay, so moving on.
So the input would be convolved with a
set of K1 filters.
The case the number of filters like I
said is usually a power of two. And
because they have depth, the number of
channels, a better notation for a filter
is probably 5 + 5 + 3 to indicate the
number of channels.
So this the things parameters to choose
is going are going to be the number of
filters, the size of the face of the
filter
and the stride. You can the filter can
scan with a stride of one or it can scan
with a stride greater than one. If it
scans with a stride greater than one,
you're going to have what will happen?
What is implicit? Upsampling or down
sampling? If I'm scanning with a stride
greater than one, what is implicit?
Down sampling. Right?
So these are all the parameters you'd
have to choose. The total number of
parameters, one for the bias, K1
filters, three channels, L squared terms
within the within each channel.
So the input may be zero padded. If you
don't want to if you want to maintain
the size, that's another design choice.
The output is going to be a bunch of
maps, one for each filter. And the way
the output is computed, first you
compute the aine term, which is
basically the inner product between the
filter and the underlying images, which
is to say you sum over all the channels.
And within each channel, you sum over
the face of the filter. And what you sum
over the face of the filter is the
product of the filter weight at that
point and the input at that point. And
of course the entire operation has an
additional bias which is generally not
typically in convolutional neural
networks you don't consider the bias. I
just included it here for completeness
sake. Once you compute the aphine term
at each location within each map you
apply an activation function to compute
the act compute the outputs at the
activation values at all of these maps.
So is this operation clear what we just
did?
Yes or no?
Right.
Then subse so the learnable parameters
the first convolution layer comprises K1
filters of size L cross L + 3. The
spatial span is L cross L depth that is
three. Right? So this is the total
number of parameters is K1 * 3 L² + 1.
All of these must be learned.
That's why not consider a bias. That's
just you know empirically we found it
doesn't make it much of a difference.
That's all. while it does complicate
things a little bit.
And then once you do that, you would
have a pooling layer. So if you were
performing max pooling, you'd be
scanning with a pooling window of size P
cross B. Within each window,
uh you want to pick the largest value
and copy it over. But the way you'd
actually do it is that you'd first find
the index, the location of the maximum
and can copy that value over. So the
parameters to choose for the pooling
layer is the size of the pooling block.
What is P cross P and the pooling
stride. How much is it going to stride
by? You may also have an additional
choice of the type of pooling. Typically
we use max pooling. And the actual
implementation is like so within each
window you first find the location of
the largest value and then copy the
value at this location over to the
output. So within each window this is
done channel by channel owner pooling is
done channel by channel and so at each
location within each window you find the
location of the maximum that's stored
here and that and this value is copied
over to this location.
So is this operation making sense to all
of you guys?
Okay. And so that's going to give you a
bunch of pulled
maps. You're going to have as many
poolled maps as the number of
convolution maps because pooling is done
channel by channel.
Then
one more jargon. The filters are often
called kernels. The output of the
individual filters are called channels.
And so the number of filters is also
called the number of channels. So the
number of filters is the number of
output channels.
And uh the number of input maps is the
same number of input channels just
terminology.
Now these are again going to be operated
on by a bunch of filters say K3 filters
and those K3 filters are going to
produce K3 output channels output maps
because the number of output maps
depends on the number of filters.
And so the parameters to choose would be
the number of filters, the size of the
filter and the stride. Right? And so uh
the so the total number of parameters in
this layer is going to be the number of
filters times the number of input
channels times the
phase size of the face of the filter.
This is for the bias. All of these must
be learned. Then you'd have another
pooling layer where the output of the
pooling will have as many channels as
the number of channels here.
And again the parameters to choose the
size of the pooling block and the
pooling stride. And you keep doing this.
Eventually when you're done the final
output is going to be flattened into a
vector. All the values and all of these
channels are just going to be stretched
out into a single vector. And then you'd
apply an MLP on it. It could just be a
simple soft max or a full MP. This is
your entire convolutional neural
network. Any questions?
This make sense to everybody?
Okay.
So, here is something. Why pooling? Why
downsampling? This is important, right?
You want more channels because if you
increase the number of channels, the
more the channels, the more the number
of features you're detecting because
each channel represents a neuron and
each neuron
detects one kind of feature. That make
sense? The number of channels is the
number of filter is the number of
features you're detecting. Did that make
sense?
Right. You can use rectangular filter
certainly. It's just going to be more
annoying that's all. Okay. So, let's say
I have an input
and the input has say k channels and the
size is n cross n.
How many values does this input have?
The total number of values.
How many values does the to does the
input have over here?
How many numbers?
KN. Correct? So now I apply a
convolution layer and I get a bunch of
maps.
So I have say
k1 maps. Okay.
And forget about edge effects. So the
size is still going to be m cross n.
Right.
So how many values do I have over here?
How many values do I have over here?
If I have K1 channels,
it's K1 MN, right? So,
have I lost information or am I
retaining information? What are the
conditions for me to have to retain
information?
What is the condition for me to retain
K1 has to be greater than or equal to K.
Otherwise, I've lost information. Right
now, I perform a pooling and say I
perform a pooling with a stride two. So,
I'm going to get a bunch of smaller
maps, right? What is the size of these
guys? If I'm using a stride two,
what's the size of
what is the size of these guys? So it's
going to be mn / 4, right?
And what is the total number of values I
have over here? What's the total number
of values I have over here?
I have k1 of these channels. So the
total number of values. It's k1
m n / 4. Right? Now can you tell me what
is the relationship between K1 and K for
me not to have lost information?
Is it K1 greater than or equal to K?
What's it? K1 must be greater than nor
equal to 4K, right? Otherwise I have
lost information.
But then so here are two things. I want
to reduce the size of the maps because I
I want to store less.
I want to increase the number of maps.
If I increase the number of maps, then
the more the maps I increase, more maps
I have, the more features I detect. But
then I can't store all of that much. I
also want to include have jitter and
variance. So I'm going to be
downsampling. So within each layer the
number if you don't want to lose
information the number of channels over
here as you know is going has to be
greater than or equal to or in general
KL for the L layer or the L as a post
you know has to be greater than or equal
to
D ^ 2 * K L -1
where D is the stride of the down
sampling. If you don't have this, you're
going to lose information. That make
sense to everybody?
Yes. Now,
right? So, those are the rules for how
you decide pulling and how how many
channels you want. In general, as you
keep going uh through the layer, you
want through the network, you want to
keep increasing the number of channels
so you can detect more and more
patterns. But then if you increase the
number of channels, you want to reduce
the size of the channels so that you
keep everything manageable. And then
there's this trade-off that the number
of channels has to be sufficient for you
to retain as much information as you
possibly can. And so the parameters to
choose are going to include the number
of convolution and downsampling or
pooling layers for each CH layer con
layer. It's you you have to decide the
number of filters, the extent of the
filter and the stride. So also for
pooling you need to decide the extent of
the pooling filter and the stride. If
you have a final MLP you have to decide
the number of layers and the number of
neurons in each layer. So here is a
final quote.
I may go a minute over. We're done. But
okay, I'll stop this early, guys. We
won't count this poll against your
attendance. What is the answer?
What's the answer? Yeah. Anyone?
They're the same. Correct. Perfect.
So, this was Yan Leon's
digit recognizer back in the day. He had
five filters of size 5 + 5. Then he had
a 2 +2 down sampling. uh
uh he had a pooling filter with stride
two for down sampling. Then he had 10
filters of size 5 + 5. Then you down
sample them by a factor of two using max
pooling and then you just pass them
through an MLP. It's a very simple
model. Training it's just as in the case
of a regular MLP. The only difference is
in the structure of the network. Your
training examples will include image
class pairs. You you pass each input
through the network and get an output.
Here you define a divergence between the
desired and true output. Then you train
network parameters through variance of
gradient descent and gradients are
computed using backdrop. The details of
which will be presented in the next
class. And so uh the story so far
convolutional neural networks are
supervised versions of computational
models of models of mamalian vision.
They include convolutional layers
comprising learned filters that scan the
outputs of the previous layer or shift
invariant pattern recognition and
pooling layers that operate over groups
of outputs from the convolution layer to
improve robustness to jitter. The
parameters of the network can be learned
through regular back propagation. I will
stop here
and